<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-08-13T16:08:06-04:00</updated><id>https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/feed.xml</id><title type="html">EDIT AI</title><subtitle>enabling historically underserved communities to direct the future of ai and biomedical studies
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">EDIT AI Mentor Profiles — Onyinyechi Owo</title><link href="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Onyi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EDIT AI Mentor Profiles — Onyinyechi Owo" /><published>2025-08-07T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-08-07T08:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Onyi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Onyi/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="background">Background</h4>

<p>Onyinyechi Owo is a Dartmouth graduate whose academic journey is shaped by a deep commitment to <strong>public service</strong>, <strong>health equity</strong>, and <strong>scientific research</strong>. She is a recipient of the prestigious <strong>Voyager Scholarship for Public Service</strong>, which included opportunities for global service — including work in <strong>Japan</strong>, <strong>Oxford</strong>, <strong>Nigeria</strong>, and across the U.S. — as well as the chance to meet <strong>President Obama and First Lady Michelle Obama</strong> on several occasions.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I’m passionate about using science and public health tools to improve wellness at the community level — especially for kids and families who are often overlooked.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Her research work reflects that commitment. Onyinyechi has contributed to stroke prevention and health literacy initiatives with <strong>Columbia University’s Neurology Department</strong>, and she was awarded Dartmouth’s <strong>Lombard Public Service Fellowship</strong> for her work supporting underserved communities.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="joining-edit-ai">Joining EDIT AI</h4>

<p>Onyinyechi joined the EDIT AI program during the summer after her sophomore year (2023), through the <strong>POWERED</strong> and <strong>OMNI</strong> programs — selective initiatives that connected a small cohort of New Hampshire students with experiential research opportunities. She was paired with EDIT AI after presenting with fellow researcher Zoe Faith on placental health.</p>

<p>That summer, she co-led an early-stage research initiative that used whole slide images of placental tissue to develop screening tools for miscarriage risk. The project leveraged <strong>QPAP</strong> — a then-cutting-edge approach that combined annotation and AI to accelerate image analysis in pathology.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“This was before AI had really taken off. We were working at the frontier — trying to annotate and screen slides more efficiently to catch critical health risks early.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here is their poster:
<br /></p>
<iframe width="100%" height="800" src="../../../assets/pdf/Onyi_and_Zoe.pdf"></iframe>

<hr />

<hr />

<h4 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h4>

<p>Onyinyechi is on the <strong>Pre-Med track</strong>, with plans to continue blending research, medicine, and service in her future career. She’s committed to a path that centers <strong>community impact</strong> and <strong>global health literacy</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="outside-the-lab">Outside the Lab</h4>

<p>Outside of academics and research, Onyinyechi is driven by storytelling, advocacy, and building bridges across cultures. Whether she’s volunteering abroad or mentoring students closer to home, her energy and warmth make her a powerful role model for aspiring scientists and changemakers alike.</p>

<hr />

<blockquote>
  <p>With a rare mix of vision, empathy, and rigor, Onyinyechi brings something special to the EDIT AI team — and to every community she touches.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>More Mentor Profiles coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><category term="news" /><category term="mentors" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meet Onyinyechi Owo — public service leader, researcher, and passionate advocate for health equity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EDIT AI Mentor Profiles — Rishy Deosthali</title><link href="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Rishy-Deosthali/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EDIT AI Mentor Profiles — Rishy Deosthali" /><published>2025-08-07T06:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-08-07T06:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Rishy-Deosthali</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Rishy-Deosthali/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="background">Background</h4>

<p>Hrishikesh (Rishy) Deosthali, 17, is a high school senior from Austin, Texas, with a growing passion for the intersection of <strong>computer science</strong> and <strong>healthcare</strong>. A self-described problem-solver, he first joined the EDIT AI program in the summer of 2024 as part of the Advanced Skills Track.</p>

<p>Initially drawn to coding, Rishy hadn’t seriously considered the healthcare side of tech until EDIT AI exposed him to real-world applications in biomedical research. That summer, he worked on a project exploring the <em>role of neurotoxic metals in ALS</em>, using an analytical approach to examine how the presence of metals like iron, zinc, and copper relate to gene expression in the disease.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I didn’t expect to be so interested in the biology side — but understanding the systems behind healthcare through code really clicked for me.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h4 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h4>

<p>Now entering his senior year, Rishy plans to pursue <strong>computer science in college</strong>, especially where it overlaps with medical innovation and data science. He’s particularly excited by the potential of AI in diagnostics and personalized medicine.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="outside-the-lab">Outside the Lab</h4>

<p>When he’s not working on code or research, you’ll probably find Rishy on the basketball court or hanging out with friends.</p>

<hr />

<blockquote>
  <p>Rishy represents a new generation of researchers — fluent in code, curious about biology, and motivated by impact. We’re thrilled to see where his journey takes him next.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>More Mentor Profiles coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><category term="news" /><category term="mentors" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meet Hrishikesh (Rishy) Deosthali — exploring the intersection of computer science and healthcare.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EDIT AI Mentor Profiles — Vivek Pujara</title><link href="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Vivek-Pujara/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EDIT AI Mentor Profiles — Vivek Pujara" /><published>2025-07-31T06:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-31T06:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Vivek-Pujara</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Vivek-Pujara/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="background">Background</h4>

<p>Meet Vivek Pujara — a 37-year-old passionate researcher whose journey bridges biology, medicine, and artificial intelligence.</p>

<p>Vivek began his academic path as a pre-med student, earning a degree in Biological Sciences at UC Irvine. Through his clinical research, he became deeply interested in neuroscience and genomics. At UC Irvine, he contributed to research on schizophrenia and bipolar disorder, helping to identify a potential biomarker. His drive for deeper insights led him to conduct independent study projects on HIV and AIDS immune evasion, oncology and genetics, and stem cells and organic 3D printing at CSU East Bay.</p>

<p>Later, after transitioning to oncology research at Cedars-Sinai, Vivek discovered a new passion: computational biology. He began exploring immuno-oncology and genomics, publishing work that characterized the mutational landscape of GI cancers.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“It was like solving a puzzle, and the more I saw the gaps in computation in these fields, the more I wanted to fill them.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Over the last five years, Vivek has focused on software engineering, with the past two dedicated to applying data science and AI to digital pathology and cancer research. Some of his recent work involves:</p>

<ul>
  <li>RNA sequencing-based research on triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC)</li>
  <li>Development of AI models using spatial transcriptomics and vision transformers</li>
  <li>Automated tools for tumor purity estimation and pathology slide annotation</li>
  <li>Predictive 3D modeling using autofluorescence and serial H&amp;E tissue section images</li>
</ul>

<p>He’s also helping build infrastructure for high-output data workflows using AWS. After interacting with Dr. Levy across several conferences, Vivek joined the EDIT AI program in 2024, where he now contributes as a mentor and technical lead for several data-centric projects.</p>

<hr />
<h4 id="outside-the-lab">Outside the Lab</h4>

<p>Vivek balances his intense scientific pursuits with creative outlets. He’s an avid musician — shredding electric guitar, singing R&amp;B and jazz, and playing acoustic sets. A diehard Lakers fan and Los Angeles native, he’s also passionate about basketball.</p>

<hr />

<blockquote>
  <p>Vivek’s journey reflects a rare blend of curiosity, technical skill, and dedication to scientific progress. His presence at EDIT AI continues to inspire the next generation of researchers.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<blockquote>
  <p>Vivek’s journey reflects a rare blend of curiosity, technical skill, and dedication to scientific progress. His presence at EDIT AI continues to inspire the next generation of researchers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>More Mentor Profiles coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><category term="news" /><category term="mentors" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In our latest Mentor Profile, meet Vivek Pujara — from clinical research to cutting-edge bioinformatics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EDIT AI Mentor Profiles — Anvith Kakkera</title><link href="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Anvith/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EDIT AI Mentor Profiles — Anvith Kakkera" /><published>2025-07-24T04:07:16-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-24T04:07:16-04:00</updated><id>https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Anvith</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2025/mentors-Anvith/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="background">Background</h4>

<p>Anvith Kakkera, 18, grew up in Northern Virginia and first joined EDIT AI as an intern in the summer of 2023. Enrolled in the Advanced Track, he dove headfirst into his research project on the <em>Cytological Evaluation of Papillary Thyroid Carcinoma: Deep Learning Analysis of Thyroid Fine-Needle Aspiration Biopsies</em> with fellow students and now mentors Anish Malepati and Aneesh kalla. While the project didn’t reach completion during the program window, Anvith’s curiosity and commitment carried it forward well beyond the summer.</p>

<p>That drive didn’t go unnoticed. In 2024, Dr. Levy invited him back as a peer mentor. Anvith accepted and went on to support two Skills Track teams, describing it as a deeply rewarding experience:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I wanted to give back. And it was so awesome to see the students grow over the summer.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This summer, he’s returned once again — now co-leading Group 5 in the Advanced Track.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h4>

<p>This fall, Anvith will begin his college journey at <strong>Dartmouth College</strong> as part of the Class of 2029. He plans to major in <strong>Biology</strong>, likely on a <strong>Pre-Med track</strong>, though he’s keeping an open mind as he continues to explore intersections between medicine, research, and technology.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="outside-the-lab">Outside the Lab</h4>

<p>Outside of research, Anvith enjoys running and has a background in track and field — a passion that mirrors his hard work when it comes to mentorship and science.</p>

<hr />

<blockquote>
  <p>Anvith’s steady growth from intern to mentor reflects the best of what EDIT AI hopes to cultivate: curiosity, perserverance, and the cultivation of skills reguarding the intersection of research, pathology, and ML. We’re proud to have him on the team.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>More Mentor Profiles coming soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><category term="news" /><category term="mentors" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Kicking off our “Mentor Profiles” series — meet Anvith Kakkera!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EDIT student to present at PSB conference in Hawaii</title><link href="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2024/PSB/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EDIT student to present at PSB conference in Hawaii" /><published>2024-12-31T21:37:16-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-31T21:37:16-05:00</updated><id>https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2024/PSB</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2024/PSB/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="overview">Overview</h4>

<p>The PSB, or <em>Pacific Symposium of Biocomputing</em>, is having it’s 30th anniversary on the 3rd, so an EDIT AI team including <a href="/people/HS_Leah_Zhang">Leah Zhang</a> (TJHSST), Edward Zhang (TJHSST), Sameeksha Garg (CMU), Sean McOsker (EDIT Mentor), and Dr. Joshua Levy worked on a project to study “what people at the (PSB) conference are talking about, and how it has changed over time.”</p>

<hr />

<p>The project consisted of 3 main parts: Leah Zhang worked with topic modeling to show how computational biology has changed over time at the conference. Sameeksha Garg mainly focused on the networking aspect of the conference, analyzing how its citation networks have changed over time. And Sean McOsker used RAG–retrieval augment generation– to make an AI chatbot for use on PSB’s website that can help people sort through the conference’s immense collection of public papers.</p>
<hr />

<p>Here is their poster, which will be displayed at the event:
<br /></p>
<iframe width="100%" height="800" src="../../../assets/pdf/PSB_30_YR_draft2_JL.pdf"></iframe>

<hr />

<p>Also, check out the program’s website <a href="https://psb.stanford.edu/">here</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Leah Zhang is new to the EDIT program this year–She heard about it and joined a friend.
When asked about her experience, she reported that she “Really appreciated the chance to work with people who weren’t just highschoolers, as well as the skills she developed in a team setting.”
She also mentioned Dartmouth’s Discovery cluster, “A really cool resource.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We wish Leah a great time at the conference, and we look forward to the new summer 2025 EDIT internship applications!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><category term="news" /><category term="PSB" /><category term="conference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Leah Zhang, an EDIT program student, will present for her group at the Pacific Symposium of Biocomputing, which is from January 3-8]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EDIT Symposium</title><link href="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2024/edit-symposium/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EDIT Symposium" /><published>2024-08-23T07:11:16-04:00</published><updated>2024-08-23T07:11:16-04:00</updated><id>https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2024/edit-symposium</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ben-m-7.github.io/editai_internship/blog/2024/edit-symposium/"><![CDATA[<p>I would like to invite everyone to attend our annual EDIT (Emerging Diagnostic and Investigative Technologies) AI summer internship virtual conference. The conference will feature research in progress presentations and breakout sessions.</p>

<p>This year’s presentations will be held on <em>August 23rd from 1-2:30 PM ET on Zoom (link below).</em> The format of this year’s presentations is a virtual conference session. After a program overview, we will listen a few live keynote presentations from our trainees. Finally, all summer students will present their work in break out rooms. Student abstracts, poster presentations and powerpoint presentations will be available on the following website:</p>

<h4 id="overview">Overview</h4>

<p>The Emerging Diagnostic and Investigative Technologies (EDIT) program is an integrated and collaborative resource in the Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine focusing on innovative diagnostic technologies for projects related to machine learning and computational diagnostic pathology, biomarker discovery, advanced ancillary testing; and genomic medicine.</p>

<hr />

<p>The EDIT AI high school summer internship program introduces students to biomedical research, focusing on AI technologies and how these technologies can be applied in the clinical setting. Students in the EDIT AI program work as members of existing labs to develop and apply AI technologies across a range of diagnostic methods and medical specialties, from cancer detection and gigapixel image manipulation to text prediction and spatial omics. Students are selected into three program tracks: 1) skills development, 2) advanced research and 3) a supportive mentor track who had previously participated in the EDIT AI program.  Students are mentored by biomedical researchers and clinicians and discuss their work with clinical collaborators in a weekly seminar series. They learn to design and pitch projects, to use and develop open-source, reproducible biomedical informatics software, and to work in a team culture that promotes broad collaboration. At the end of the summer, students present in a center-wide poster and presentation session. Mentors meet with students prior to these presentations and students are encouraged to consider how their work would impact “big picture” clinical practices rather than only focusing on computational aspects. Students are challenged to think critically about the successful design of clinically impactful technologies. Students have presented research at national conferences, participated in science fairs, co-authored academic papers, matriculated to college, and successfully applied for scholarships. Our goal is that students’ experiences in EDIT AI will continue to shape how they engage project stakeholders both during and after their time at Dartmouth.</p>
<hr />

<p>We were very impressed by the aptitude and diverse range of interests of all summer program students. They worked alongside a team of clinicians, research scientists, undergraduate, Master’s, MD, PhD and MD-PhD students, all of whom aspire to improve public health through advancement and application of AI technologies. This summer, students worked on projects and listened to more than 30 seminar presentations from academia, medical and industry experts.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We have run this pilot program for the past 5 years. With support from the Dartmouth Cancer Center, the EDIT AI summer program for high school students has experienced remarkable growth, expanding from 6 participants in its first year to nearly 90 annual participants per year across 21 states.
Last year’s presentations were very compelling and well received and we expect similar results this year. 
Feel free to stop by to support these young scientists. Please share this invitation with your colleagues.
—Joshua Levy PhD, Louis J. Vaickus MD PhD , Matthew Hayden MD PhD</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><category term="news" /><category term="communication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Culminating symposium is scheduled for today!]]></summary></entry></feed>